Finding Aid for William J. Pierce Papers, 1930s-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William J. Pierce Papers 1930s-1990, 1950s-1960s
Pierce, William J.
6 linear feet
0325 Aa 2
Professor of law at the University of Michigan; director of the Legislative Research Center; president and executive director of the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws. Biographical and personal materials; subject files relating to his association with the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws and his work in the drafting of uniform legislation among the states in specific areas.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Pierce (donor no. 8967 ) and came to the library in May 2000.
The collection is open to research.
William J. Pierce was born December 4, 1921 in Flint, Michigan. Following wartime service, he received his BA from the University of Michigan in 1947, then entered the U-M Law School, receiving the degree of Juris Doctor in 1949.
Pierce began his career at the University as a research assistant (1949-1950) and then research associate (1950-1951) in the Law School. In 1951, he was appointed to the Law School faculty as an assistant professor, eventually becoming full professor in 1958. In 1952, Pierce was also named assistant director of the Law School's Legislative Research Center. He became director in 1957. He retired from the university in 1989.
In 1953, Pierce was appointed Michigan Commissioner on Uniform State Laws and also a member of the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws (NCCUSL). Both within the Law School where he taught courses on the subject and professionally as a member of the NCCUSL, Pierce's primary specialty was in the area of legislation and legislative drafting. Pierce was a member of the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws for more than forty years, serving as chairman of the executive committee, 1965-1967, president 1967-1969, and then following his term as president, as executive director, where he served until 1992.
The Pierce papers document his work for the preservation of state parks, most notably in correspondence with Genevieve Gillette, and his work with the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws (NCCUSL). The paper have been organized into two series: Biographical/Personal and National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws.
Subjects:
Pierce, William J.; Nuclear energy--Government policy.; Groves, Leslie R., 1896-1970.; National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws.; Uniform state laws.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.
Contributors:
Gillette, Genevieve, 1898-
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series, in addition to vitae and bibliographical information, includes a file documenting his work on behalf of the preservation of Michigan parks, including correspondence with Genevieve Gillette. There is also a file that includes a summary of interview conducted by Pierce with General Leslie R. Groves on July 16, 1953 regarding post World War II legislation on the peaceful uses of atomic energy.
  - Vita, correspondence, etc. (Box 1)
  - Letters received upon occasion of his retirement 1990 (Box 1)
  - Course material (Box 1)
  - Work on behalf of Michigan Parks and the National Parks Foundation (Box 1)
  - Summary of interview with General Leslie R. Groves re the May-Johnson bill (on atomic energy) July 16, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous personal (Box 1)
- National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws Files
  A portion of the NCCUSL papers predate Pierce's involvement with the organization and were undoubtedly given to Pierce when he accepted various responsibilities within the organization. Other files were sent to Pierce in his capacity as executive director (and for his information) and do not represent his work in the drafting of legislation. A few notable files illustrate Pierce's own contribution to the drafting of uniform legislation. Important examples of these were in the areas of the division of income for tax purposes and the probate code.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1)
  - Absentee Voters Act (proposed) (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Acknowledgment Act (Box 1)
  - Administration Procedure Act 2 (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Adoption Act (Box 1)
  - Attendance of Witnesses from Without a State in Criminal Cases 1931 (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights Legislation (Box 1)
  - Civil Litigation Costs (Box 1)
  - Choice of Forum Act (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Commercial Code (Box 1)
  - Complex Litigation (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Consent to Medical Treatment Act (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Consumer Credit Code 1971 (Box 1)
  - Consumer Credit Code miscellaneous 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Contribution Among Torteasors (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Control of Perpetuities Act (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Controlled Substance Act (Box 1)
  - Cy-Pres Doctrine (Box 1)
  - Damage to Surface Estate Act 1988 (Box 1)
  - Day Care Licensing 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Defamation Act 1990 (Box 1)
  - Disclosures of Depositors Earnings (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Disclaimer Acts, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Divorce Recognition Act 1948 (Box 1)
  - (Uniform) Drug Dependence Treatment and Rehabilitation Act (Box 1)
  - Drug paraphernalia Act (Box 1)
  - Division of Income for Tax Purposes 1965-1974 (some years lacking) (Box 2)
  - Electronic Data Processing Committee (NCCUSL) (Box 3)
  - Enforcement of Foreign Judgments Act 1948 (Box 3)
  - Enforcement of Support Act 1952 (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Escheats of Unclaimed Postal Savings Accounts Act (Box 3)
  - Expert Testimony Act 1937 (Box 3)
  - Factory-Built Modular Housing (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Federal-State Relationship (Box 3)
  - Foreign Claims-Statute of Limitations on Foreign Claims Act (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Foreign Money-Judgment Recognition Act (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Health Records Act (Box 3)
  - Installment Sales Finance Act (Box 3)
  - International Law-Unification of Private International Law (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Jury Selection and Service Act (Box 3)
  - Landlord Tenant Relationship Act (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Land Sales Practices Act (Box 3)
  - Marriage and Divorce 1970 (Box 3)
  - (Uniform) Newsmen's Privilege Act (Box 3)
  - Non-Probate Transfers (Box 3)
  - Perpetuities. Uniform Statutory Rule Against Perpetuities (Box 4)
  - Post-Mortem Examinations Office Act (Box 4)
  - Preliminary Injunction Relief Act (Box 4)
  - Preservations. Historic Preservations Agreement Act (Box 4)
  - (Uniform) Pretrial Detention Act (Box 4)
  - Principal. Revised Uniform Principal and Income Act (Box 4)
  - (Uniform) Privacy Proposal; Uniform Privacy Act, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - (Uniform) Probate Code (Box 5)
  - Procurement. Model Procurement Code (Box 5)
  - Protective Proceedings Act (Box 5)
  - (Uniform) Real Estate Time-Share Act (Box 5)
  - Reciprocal Enforcement of Support Act (Box 5)
  - Reciprocal State Investment Act (Box 5)
  - Recognition of Foreign Divorce (Box 5)
  - Rights of the Terminally Ill (Box 5)
  - (Uniform) Securities Act (Box 5)
  - (Uniform) Securities Act (cont.) (Box 6)
  - (Uniform) Simplification of Land Transfer Act (Box 6)
  - (Model) State Tax Procedure Act (Box 6)
  - (Model) State Trade-Mark Act (Box 6)
  - State Transfer of Complex Litigation (Box 6)
  - Statute of Limitations Act 1939 (Box 6)
  - Statutory Construction Act (Box 6)
  - Statutory (proposed) Wills Act (Box 6)
  - Surface Use and Damages (Box 6)
  - Trade Secrets Act (Box 6)
  - (Uniform) Traffic Laws (Box 6)
  - Trustees Accounting Act 1936 (Box 6)
  - Unincorporated Business Associations Act (Box 6)
  - Vehicle Code (Box 6)
  - Vital Statistics Act 1942 (Box 6)
  - Workmen's Compensation (Box 6)
  - Wrongful Death Act (Box 6)